{
  "reference_number": "12435",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "We need to reduce emissions of all pollution but especially greenhouse/climate changing gases ASAP. The Government should show\n strong leadership and set a highly-aggressive reduction target NOW, which should bind all Government agencies, other laws, and\n\n private businesses/organisations."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases BEFORE 2050 is achievable with the will. We should be legislating for net zero by\n 2050 as a minimum target, not an aspiration."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We have seen that previous NZ Governments have used suspicious carbon units from overseas as a substitute for actually taking\n\n action within NZ. We should focus on leading the world and taking ACTION WITHIN NZ and RELYING ON NO ONE ELSE to make\n greenhouse gas reductions. The time for strong action within NZ is now."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We have to set and hit a target. The world's future is at stake. If we exceed the target or reach it early, then great. But revision would\n likely mean weakening the target by future governments, so no revision."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Industry should not have the excuse of not knowing what the legislative roadmap is. Make the path to zero emissions clear, and let\n everyone get on with the job."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree with most of the considerations, but not the \"economic circumstances\" portion. Technology will advance and industry will\n\nadapt. If particular sectors of the economy suffer, then it is likely because they have been externalising their costs in terms of\nemissions and not accounting for them. Economic circumstances should therefore NOT form part of the considerations. In addition,\nenergy policy should ONLY form part of the considerations with the goal of reducing the carbon intensity of the economy to phase out\n\ncarbon usage to net zero ASAP. I agree with the other four considerations."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Set a clear roadmap for industry and individuals to follow. Let people get on with the transition to no carbon with no moaning about\n\nnot knowing."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Talk with any interested stakeholder but ultimately do NOT BE SWAYED FROM THE VISION OF ZERO CARBON ASAP. Industries which\nhave lazily emitted pollution (or any sort) will complain, but they need to be educated and become more innovative in order to react.\n\nOur future depends on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree with the eight main points but NOT with the point \"business competitiveness\". Legacy industries which rely on lazily emitting\ngreenhouse gases must not be allowed to capture or derail the Climate Change Commission. The focus must be locked on the\n\ngreater good of decarbonizing the economy and the country as a whole. Commissioners should be selected for their ability to bring\nabout change, not defend the polluting status quo."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. Lack of Government information provision to councils etc. in the recent past has led to climate-vulnerable developments being\napproved. Risk assessments etc. in particular need to be funded, carried out urgently, and action taken based on them."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This bill is a rare opportunity to effect significant change in NZ's climate change-causing actions. It is time to become a leader in\n\nsaving the climate form irreversible damage. I hope that this bill is passed in as strong a form as possible."
    }
  ]
}
